Today's דף Daf פ״ד, Peh Dalet, we pick up on the very
last line of פ״ג עמוד ב׳. Peh Gimmel Amud Bet. We had
a משנה Mishnah that taught that all מנחות Menachot can come from
old grain, new grain, grain from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, grain from
חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, with the exception of עומר Omer and שתי
הלחם Shtei Halechem where the whole point is it is the new
grain, the new barley and the new wheat. So that has to
come from ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and it has to come from
the new grain. However, we did introduce some very interesting Tannaitic opinions
that say that the עומר Omer and שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem can
come from the old grain. So it's quite ironic, you need them
to allow the new grain to be brought according to this, but
they themselves can actually not relate to the new grain directly, it
can come from the old grain. This was the opinion of a
number of תנאים Tannaim quoted in the גמרא. Gemara. And now we
continue with that and we look at the other aspect of it,
which is: does it have to come from Israel? Interesting. So although
happy יום ירושלים Yom Yerushalayim everybody, and today we will be discussing
somewhat on the distinctiveness of Israel, not ירושלים Yerushalayim I'm sorry to
say. But anyway, a little bit ties in.
So last line of פ״ג, Peh Gimmel, moved me with the ירושלים
Yerushalayim anyway.
There we go. Okay, so the last line of פ״ג עמוד ב׳:
Peh Gimmel Amud Bet: עד כאן לא פליגי אלא בחדש. Ad kan
lo peligi ela bechadash.
The only debate so far we've seen in the תנאים Tannaim is
whether the עומר Omer and שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem needs to come
from the new grain or can even come from the old grain.
אבל בארץ, Aval ba'aretz, but the fact that it has to come
from grain that grew in Israel, לא פליגי, lo peligi, that they
don't debate that by the עומר Omer and שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem
at least, it must come from Israel. דעומר ושתי הלחם מארץ אין
מחוץ לארץ לא, De'omer veShtei Halechem me'aretz in michutz la'aretz lo, only
from Israel, not from outside of Israel. כמאן? Keman? Who is this
going by? דלא כהאי תנא, Delo kehai tanna, not like the following
תנא. Tanna. We have another תנא Tanna that debates even the idea
of whether it has to come from grain grown in Israel. דתניא,
Detanya, we taught in a ברייתא: Braita: רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר:
Rabbi Yose b'Rebbi Yehuda omer: עומר בא מחוץ לארץ. Omer ba michutz
la'aretz. The עומר Omer can come from outside of Israel. ומה אני
מקיים כי תבואו אל הארץ, Umah ani mekayyem 'ki tavou el ha'aretz',
when you come to the land, וקצרתם את קצירה והבאתם את עומר
ראשית קצירכם אל הכהן, uktzartem et ktzirah vehevetem et omer reshit ktzirchem
el hakohen,
so it frames it in terms of coming to the land, to
tell you שלא נתחייבו בעומר קודם שנכנסו לארץ, shelo nitchayyu ba'omer kodem
shenichnesu la'aretz, that the obligation did not begin until they entered the
land, but once they entered the land and they became obligated, it
can come from anywhere.
And now האי תנא, hai Tanna, so it's referring from where we
began.
I don't know, it's a funny way to introduce it, so we're
sort of saying our משנה Mishnah is not like the following תנאים.
Tannaim. על כל פנים, At kol panim,
as I said, maybe it's a good question. I don't know if
he has a system about that.
Now the גמרא Gemara interestingly feels a need to explain the logic
of this position. Because you know, both of these ideas, that the
עומר Omer and שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem can come from old grain
and can come from חוץ לארץ, Chutz La'aretz, you might be able
to get out of the פסוקים Psukim like yesterday we said oh
the פסוקים Psukim that said חדש chadash ומנחה ואפוקי. vemincha ve'afakei.
But you know, it still raises serious questions about what the logic
is here. So here the גמרא Gemara does feel a need to
explain about the logic of grain that comes from חוץ לארץ Chutz
La'aretz and for God's sake, you know, it's one thing to say
it doesn't have to come from the new grain, but at least
it represents the grain of the land, you know? As the whole
idea is around these agricultural holidays and the land of Israel and
the grain and this time of life, of this time of the
year. So what is the idea that it can come from חוץ
לארץ? Chutz La'aretz? So here the גמרא Gemara gives an
explanation: דקסבר חדש בחוץ לארץ דאורייתא. Dechasavar chadash bechutz la'aretz de'oraita. He's
of the opinion that חדש Chadash outside of Israel is דאורייתא, de'oraita,
which as we know is a major debate of תנאים Tannaim and
of פוסקים. Poskim. היא? Hi? דכתיב Dichativ ממושבותיכם. mimoshvoteichem. It says from
the places where you dwell, כל מקום שאתם יושבין, kol makom she'attem
yoshvin, wherever you live, even outside of Israel. משמע דכי תבואו, Mashma
de 'ki tavou', so when it says when you come to the
land, זמן ביאה היא. zeman biah hi. It doesn't mean that the
מצוה mitzvah of the prohibitions of חדש Chadash apply only in the
land, it means that once you come to the land, then the
prohibitions will apply but they will apply all over. So once the
prohibitions of חדש Chadash apply all over, so by analogy or by
parallel,
וכיון דאורייתא היא, vekivan de'oraita hi, and since דאורייתא de'oraita it applies
outside of Israel, the prohibitions of חדש, Chadash, אקרובי נמי מקריבין. ikruvvei
nami makrivin. So then you can also bring it from there, because
the עומר Omer is מתיר mattir not only grain of Israel, it's
מתיר mattir grain even outside of Israel. So therefore it can come
from grain outside of Israel. Now you know Michael says that that
is
somewhat compelling or at least certainly a significant, and I would say,
I would elaborate on that for a minute.
First of all, in terms of the פלפלי pelpali difficulty, they couldn't
you know, these things like the night before, you know, to get
it all the way from, you know—
Yeah, but presumably that you're not doing either, I mean, presumably this
all falls under the idea of ישן yashan although it doesn't say
that. So anyway, first of all, let's talk about the פסוקים. Psukim.
פסוקים Psukim say, right, ממושבותיכם תביאו לחם תנופה. mimoshvoteichem tavi'u lechem tenuphah.
Exactly,
that by the שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem. What does ממושבותיכם mimoshvoteichem mean?
By the עומר Omer it says והבאתם את עומר ראשית קצירכם אל
הכהן והניף את העומר לפני ה׳ לרצונכם... vehevetem et omer reshit ktzirchem
el hakohen veheniph et ha'omer lifnei Hashem lirtzonchem... ולחם וקלי וכרמל לא
תאכלו עד עצם היום הזה עד הביאכם את קרבן אלהיכם חקת
עולם לדרתיכם בכל משבתיכם. velechem vekali vecharmel lo tochlu ad etzem hayom
hazeh ad haviechem et korban Eloheichem chukkat olam ledoroteichem bechol moshvoteichem. Right,
so ממושבותיכם moshvoteichem actually there does say it relating to the prohibition,
not relating to the bringing of the עומר. Omer. But you know,
it is true that if you're going to prohibit out of the
land— to then maybe the new grain can come, or the grain
can come from grain out of the land, although again normally we're
inclined to think that the תורה Torah is actually sort of setting
up almost like a hierarchy, you know, that fundamentally it's about grain
in Israel and mastering the grain in Israel, but all the other
lands somehow sort of are derivative from Israel. So therefore they're prohibited
because Israel's prohibited. Once Israel becomes permissible, they become permissible, but to
see them at some type of a derivative state, especially if you
consider that from the תורה's Torah perspective, right, I mean גלות galus
is an unnatural state. So basically the Jewish people are living in
Israel. Some Jewish people are living outside of Israel, that's unnatural or
unusual. And therefore fundamentally we focus on the bringing the עומר Omer
from Israel, the prohibition in Israel, but it's possible that if it's
prohibited in Israel that then also it extends to others. That's how
we normally think about it, that we can sort of deal with
that imbalance as you would, that the prohibition applies outside of Israel
but the עומר Omer can only be brought from Israel. But here
what he's saying is actually, no, maybe we don't see it as
a hierarchy. We basically see that the תורה Torah is saying all
grain is prohibited wherever you are until the new grain is brought,
and that new grain can be so, if it's prohibited everywhere, the
new grain can be brought from any new harvest. Again, that you
know I find that, I have to sort of tell you, especially
on יום ירושלים, Yom Yerushalayim, ideologically disturbing, you know, that the idea
that we're basically saying that you know that there is, the תורה
Torah in a way sort of cares from the Jewish perspective, I'm
not saying from the non-Jewish perspective, from the perspective of the Jews
and the Jewish people, it cares about the idea of harvest outside
of Israel. You know, because I think the whole mentality, the whole
sort of worldview of the תורה Torah is that the Jewish people
are seen as to be in the state of Israel, and that's
their harvest and that's sort of and that's what the focus is.
Anyway, this is the position of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose
b'rabbi Yehuda, and it's worth noting that for a number of פוסקים
poskim who are trying to defend why we're so lenient about חדש
chadash nowadays, they do point to this גמרא Gemara for the following
two reasons. First of all, the גמרא Gemara says קסבר, kasavar,
he's of the opinion that חדש chadash in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz
is דאורייתא, de'oraita, which makes it sound that that's not necessarily the
opinion. It's you know his opinion, he's a single opinion, and that's
his opinion, but it's not necessarily the standard. And number two, the
fact that they'll say, ah, this גמרא Gemara links the two. Where
if חדש chadash is אסור assur in חוץ לארץ chutz la'aretz then
you can bring the עומר Omer from חוץ לארץ. chutz la'aretz. Since
we rule like our משנה Mishna that you can only bring the
עומר Omer from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, logically we also rule that
חדש chadash is only prohibited biblically in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Okay,
so that they actually want to use this גמרא Gemara as a
way of arguing why חדש chadash is not so קביעה, kebi'a, I
mean it's still דרבנן, de'rabbanan, but why we could be so lenient
outside of the Land. Again, that's not necessarily true. The גמרא Gemara
says he holds that they're linked, but presumably everybody else disagrees with
the idea that these are linked concepts. But nevertheless, this is a
גמרא Gemara that is used within that discussion. Okay, now we go
on. So now we have, very fascinatingly,
does yes, question.
Does that imply that there will always be a diaspora?
Well, that is what I said is disturbing about his position. It
doesn't imply that there will always be a diaspora, right, but it
just implies that for him, it's not underscoring the, if you would,
unnatural state of the diaspora, which is part of what I said
is disturbing about that position. Okay, now again, it's worth speculating whether
רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose b'rabbi Yehuda, although he allows it
to be from חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, maybe he requires it to
be from the new grain, right? Because if anything, you know, if
you asked what is the primary idea of עומר Omer and שתי
הלחם, Shtei Halechem, if you had to pick one, is the primary
idea it's the new harvest or the primary idea is that it's
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael grain?
I say the new harvest is the primary idea. It's ראשית קצירכם.
Reshit ketzirchem. So interestingly, this תנא tanna might hold you can come
from חוץ לארץ, chutz la'aretz, but maybe he would hold it has
to be the new grain. And there was another תנא tanna that
held it could be old grain, but it has to be ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael grain. So either of these positions are
strange, and our משנה Mishna rejects both of them. Now the גמרא
Gemara will continue exploring these alternate positions. So let's take a look.
תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we taught over there, in a משנה Mishna
in שקלים. Shekalim. שקלים Shekalim talks about the collecting of the funds
on an annual basis from the people for the תרומת הלשכה, Trumat
Halishka, for money that would go for communal purposes, primarily for the
תמיד, Tamid, the daily sacrifices, communal sacrifices morning and afternoon, but those
funds could also be used to serve other communal needs, for well,
particularly communal בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash קרבן korban needs. So let's take
a look what the משנה Mishna says. תנן התם, Tnan hatam, we
taught over there: שומרי ספיחין בשביעית, Shomrei sefichin bishvi'it, the people that
guard the ספיחין. sefichin. ספיחין Sefichin are plants that grow on their
own without being planted, because you can't plant on שמיטה. Shmita. So
the people that guard those plants, now what are they guarding them
for? They are guarding them, it's not explicit here, but the context
is and is they're guarding them to use them for the עומר.
Omer. So how are you going to cut the עומר Omer on
שמיטה? Shmita? So where are you going to get the grain? Nobody's
planting the grain. So the grain you're going to get is grain
that grew by itself, ספיחין, sefichin, you know sometimes seeds fall in
a natural process and stuff will grow, wild grain even if you're
not cultivating and planting it. So you use that grain for the
עומר. Omer. Now who's going to watch it to make sure that
the עניים aniyim don't grab it all up? You know, how are
you going to make sure that it's protected? So you get some
people from the. בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you hire them with the
שקלים, Shekalim, which is what this is about, and they're going to
protect this grain so that we can use it now for the
עומר. Omer. We'll talk about how we avoid שמיטה Shmita problems in
a minute.
It's not the people who just watch it to make sure that
people aren't just harvesting it normally?
No, this is specifically to protect it for bringing it for the
עומר. Omer. That's the context. Okay, so שומרי ספיחים בשביעית shomrei sefichin
b'shevi'is נוטלין שכרן notlin secharan מתרומת הלשכה mitrumas halishka
from these communal funds that are raised each year for communal sacrifices
because this ultimately is in order to bring the עומר, Omer, which
is a communal sacrifice. Okay. Now, רמי ליה, rami leh, now we're
going to explore this idea about bringing the עומר Omer on שמיטה.
Shmita. So רמי ליה רמי בר חמא לרב חסדא, rami leh Rami
bar Chama l'Rav Chisda, רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked the
following question to רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. תנן, tenan, שומרי ספיחין בשביעית
נוטלין שכרן מתרומת הלשכה. shomrei sefichin b'shevi'is notlin secharan mitrumas halishka. We
had this משנה mishna we just saw it. ורמינהו, uraminihu, I'll ask
you on that. What does the תורה Torah say by שמיטה? Shmita?
לאכלה, le'ochla, that it should be והיתה שבת הארץ לכם לאכלה, vehayesa
shabbos ha'aretz lachem le'ochla, it should be for you to eat, קדושת
שביעית kedushas shevi'is demands that the produce be eaten, ולא לשריפה, v'lo
lisreifa,
those two words are not in the תורה, Torah, but that's the
rabbinic laws on it, that you cannot burn שמיטה Shmita produce. So
we have a problem. You're going to bring the עומר Omer from
the שמיטה, Shmita, what do you do with the עומר? Omer? You
take a קמיצה kmitza and you burn a קמיצה. kmitza. So some
of this has קדושת שמיטה kedushas Shmita and you're not eating all
of it, you're burning some of it. So how are you going
to... how can you fulfill לאכלה? le'ochla?
Yeah, that did not feel, does not feel that that satisfies לאכלה
le'ochla of the תורה. Torah. So let's see what the answer is.
אמר ליה, amar leh, so he said back to him, רחמנא אמר
לכו לדורותיכם, Rachmana amar lachem l'doroseichem,
the תורה Torah says that this should be, you know, for all
generations bringing the עומר, Omer, ואת אמרת תבטל, v'at amart tivatel, you
want it to, you know, to nullify it? You want to stop
it? Now of course, he wasn't saying I want to stop it,
he's trying to figure it out, you know, how does it work?
But okay, saying of course we have to do it, what type
of question is that? So אמר ליה, amar leh, that's what he
said back, ומי קאמינא אנא תבטל? umi ka'amina ana tivatel?
I didn't say that we should nullify it. No, no, that wasn't
my suggestion. ליתי מדישתקד, leyasi midishtakad,
let's bring it from last year's crop. So here, it's going back
to those other תנאים Tannaim that say that the עומר Omer can
come from last year's crop. So he is saying, you know, here's
actually a case where maybe it should prove that they're right because
how else can you bring it from this year's crop on a
שמיטה Shmita if you're not going to satisfy the demands of לאכלה?
le'ochla?
What? We get a harder problem in יובל. Yovel.
Well he says bring from two years back. Okay, so anyway, so
he's saying look, this should show that you could bring it from
last year's crop. So he says no, בעינא כרמל וליכא. be'ina karmel
v'leika. So interestingly, as opposed to yesterday where the emphasis was on
פסוקים pesukim that said ראשית, reishis, the first cutting, here we're emphasizing
other פסוקים pesukim that emphasize it has to be fresh grain. There's
a word that says כרמל, karmel, we're going to see it in
a minute, it says כרמל, karmel, which the גמרא Gemara interprets to
mean sort of, you know, fresh, moist, and therefore it would not
be that if it was last year's grain. So he says וליתי
מכרמל דישתקד. v'leyasi mikarmel dishtakad. Maybe it was what was fresh last
year. Not fresh now.
I don't know if he means fresh fish from last year.
Right, exactly. I don't know if he means it's still fresh, but
it's from last year. I don't know how they did it, or
it was fresh. Everything was once fresh.
I'm not exactly sure.
Ground into flour, the idea of freshness is a little bit milky.
Right, not moist anymore.
So can you really tell the difference?
Oh, so you mean that maybe it was ground into flour last
year so it stayed fresh? Meaning,
but you're not taking grain from last year, you're taking flour from
last year. Is that what you're saying? So that when it was
made into flour, it was fresh. Right. Oh, that's a good point.
So not that we're taking last year's grain which now would be
dry, we're taking last year's flour. So when it was converted from
wheat grain into flour, or from not wheat, barley into flour, it
was fresh. Maybe that is the point. Okay. אמר קרא, amar kra,
no, he's not happy. He says the פסוק pasuk says כרמל תקריב.
karmel takriv. It says אביב קלוי באש גרש כרמל תקריב את מנחת
ביכוריך. aviv kalui ba'esh geres karmel takriv es minchas bikurecha.
So the word תקריב, takriv, you shall offer it, comes right after
the word of כרמל, karmel, which means fresh and moist. So it
has to be brought while it is moist. It cannot have been
moist last year. בעינא כרמל בשעת הקרבה וליכא.
be'ina
karmel b'sha'as hakrava v'leika.
You need it to have been fresh at the time when it's
being brought, not that it was fresh last year, וליכא. v'leika. So
he rejects that and therefore he says that no, you're going to
bring it anyway and you're stuck, you have to use this year.
I don't believe you can use last year and if you have
no choice, so you have no choice and you can even violate
לאכלה. le'ochla. So I want to say a couple of things about
this about the עומר Omer on... well you know, let's finish the
דברי תורה divrei Torah about last year and then we'll go back
and analyze the idea of עומר Omer on שמיטה. Shmita. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this.
איתמר, itmar, we talked. רבי יוחנן אמר כרמל תקריב. Rabbi Yochanan amar
karmel takriv. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says it has to be
this year's based on the פסוק, pasuk, not ראשית, reishis, but the
פסוק pasuk we've been quoting now, fresh, it has to be fresh
when it's brought, so it has to be this year's grain. רבי
אלעזר אמר ראשית קצירכם. Rabbi Elazar amar reishis katzirchem. So another... he
agrees with the position it have to be this year's grain but
he's not emphasizing the word כרמל, karmel, but the word ראשית, reishis,
the first of your cutting. ראשית קצירך ולא סוף קצירך reshit k'tzircha
v'lo sof k'tzircha the first of your cutting and not at the
end of your cutting meaning if you would bring last year's grain
so the grain you're bringing is now being brought at the end
of that harvest season right the last year's harvest season was over
so by the time you're bringing it it's not the beginning of
this harvest season it's the end of its harvest season when you
bring it it has to be the beginning of the harvest season
so again a similar idea but based on ראשית reshit not based
on
כרמל. Carmel. מתיב רבה metiv Raba so Rabba asked on this now
again it's so funny because here the גמרא Gemara is getting very
worked up by which where the דרשה drasha is coming from but
the law is everybody
is agreeing to the הלכה halacha that it has to be this
year's. So Rabba's question is also not going to be about the
הלכה halacha it's going to be about the פסוק. pasuk. So let's
see what Rabba's question is. ואם תקריב מנחת בכורים v'im takriv minchat
bikurim if you bring the מנחת בכורים minchat bikurim you know which
is referring to the עומר Omer
so the way חז"ל Chazal understand it. So let's take a look
at what this ברייתא braita does how it unpacks the פסוק pasuk
relating to the עומר. Omer. במנחת העומר הכתוב מדבר b'minchat ha'omer hakatuv
midaber
so this is talking about the עומר Omer that's just asserted that
it says ואם תקריב מנחת בכורים לה' אביב קלוי באש גרש כרמל
תקריב את מנחת בכוריך.
v'im takriv minchat bikurim la'Hashem aviv kalui ba'esh geresh carmel
takriv et minchat bikurecha.
So חז"ל Chazal understand that that's talking about the bringing of the
עומר. Omer. מהיכן היא באה me'heichan hi ba'ah now what type of
grain do you use for the עומר? Omer? מן השעורים min hase'orim
barley. Interestingly
you know again I don't know I always grew up knowing the
עומר Omer was from barley. Strange thing of course I know but
okay I had a ישיבה yeshiva education and I assumed it was
in a פסוק pasuk somewhere but believe it or not the תורה
Torah never says what you bring the עומר. Omer.
It says ראשית קצירך אביב קלוי באש גרש כרמל reshit k'tzircha aviv
kalui ba'esh geresh carmel it never says that it's the barley. So
that we have to figure out from a פסוק. pasuk. Okay so
מהיכן היא באה מן השעורים. me'heichan hi ba'ah min hase'orim. אתה אומר
מן השעורים atah omer min hase'orim
you say the עומר Omer comes from barley או אינו אלא מן
החיטים o eino ela min hachitim maybe it comes from wheat? רבי
אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer Rabbi Eliezer says נאמר אביב במצרים ne'emar
aviv b'Mitzrayim it says the word אביב aviv right in Egypt. כי
השעורה אביב והפשתה גבעול ki hase'orah aviv v'hapishtah givol right remember why
the why the
what was it the the which was it that the ברד barad
destroyed I know what did it destroy did it not destroy the
the the barley it says והפשתה והכוסמת לא נכו כי אפילות הנה
v'hapishtah v'hakusemet lo nuku ki afilot henah right
so because the barley was ripe and it was fully standing therefore
the ברד barad destroyed it but the other grain which was not
yet ripened was not destroyed by the by the by the ברד
barad right actually like interesting I only just put it together but
that you know works since the barley is ripe around ניסן Nissan
and that's so ברד barad is right near the end of the
מכות makkot right about when they were ready to go out okay
good so the timing works okay anyway so it says אביב aviv
in מצרים Mitzrayim right which is talking about the barley which was
smitten by the ברד. barad. ונאמר אביב לדורות v'ne'emar aviv l'dorot and
here it says אביב קלוי באש. aviv kalui ba'esh. מה אביב האמור
במצרים שעורים mah aviv ha'amur b'Mitzrayim se'orim the same way over in
Egypt שעורים se'orim it means barley אף אביב האמור לדורות אינה באה
אלא מן השעורים af aviv ha'amur l'dorot eino ba ela min hase'orim
so here too the word אביב aviv means you know which again
פסח הוא חודש האביב Pesach hu chodesh ha'aviv so all these things
of אביב aviv the ripening means here in the context the ripening
of the barley. Okay so that's how we know it's barley.
ילך ופסול וזהו תקריב yelech v'pasul v'zehu takriv yeah that starts
it so that's actually what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is more or
less going to do. רבי עקיבא אומר Rabbi Akiva omer מצינו יחיד
yachid שמביא חובתו מן החיטים ומביא חובתו מן השעורים matzinu yachid she'meivi
chovato min hachitim u'meivi chovato min hase'orim we know that there's an
individual barley מנחה mincha obligatory barley מנחה mincha and an individual obligatory
wheat מנחה. mincha. What's the obligatory barley מנחה? mincha? So that is
in a case
that's that's מנחת סוטה מנחת קנאות minchat sotah minchat kna'ot so not
that everybody has to bring it but anyway there can be an
obligation to bring a barley מנחה mincha and there's a wheat מנחה
mincha which is a מנחת חוטא minchat choteh when you bring a
מנחה mincha for a sin when the few places that that occurs
that you're able to bring that you have a קרבן עולה ויורד
korban oleh v'yored and you could bring a מנחה mincha for a
sin it would be out of wheat. So by an individual there's
exists an obligatory מנחה mincha by barley and an obligatory מנחה mincha
by wheat. So similarly ואף ציבור v'af tzibur
so by parallel the community מביא חובתו מן החיטים meivi chovato min
hachitim they will bring they will have an obligatory מנחה mincha from
wheat ומביא חובתו מן השעורים u'meivi chovato min hase'orim and an obligatory
מנחה mincha from barley. אם אתה אומר מן החיטים im atah omer
min hachitim now if you tell me that the עומר Omer comes
from wheat לא מצינו ציבור tzibur שמביא חובתו מן השעורים lo matzinu
tzibur she'meivi chovato min hase'orim and we'll never have a barley מנחה.
mincha. We already have a wheat מנחה mincha by the ציבור tzibur
the שתי הלחם shtei halechem that is explicit so by parallel we
need there to be an obligatory מנחה mincha for the ציבור tzibur
by barley. So therefore he's saying we can assume it's barley because
of the parallel to the individual. We have an individual מנחה mincha
of wheat and barley we can assume we have a ציבור מנחה
tzibur mincha of wheat and barley. Wheat we already know therefore the
עומר Omer have to be barley. That's how he knows it's barley.
דבר אחר davar acher
last דרשה drasha to show that it's barley. אם אתה אומר עומר
im atah omer omer I need to be guttural here. אם אתה
אומר עומר בא מן החיטים im atah omer omer ba min hachitim
so if you say the עומר Omer comes from wheat אין שתי
הלחם בכורים ein shtei halechem bikurim and the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
not be ביכורים, bikurim, okay, they won't be, it won't be the
first that is brought because there will something have been brought from
the wheat beforehand. Now again, it is a little ironic because you
cannot bring anything from the new grain on the מזבח mizbeach until
the שתי הלחם. shtei halechem. Let's remember that's how they function. The
עומר Omer allows new grain to be eaten outside the בית המקדש.
Beis Hamikdash. It was brought of barley but it allows all new
grain, wheat, barley, all new grain to be eaten outside of the
מזבח mizbeach after the עומר Omer is brought. The שתי הלחם shtei
halechem allows new grain to be used in sacrifices. Until the שתי
הלחם shtei halechem is brought, no new grain could be used, not
even of barley. So the little irony here is is that the
שתי הלחם shtei halechem allows new grain, it's called ביכורים, bikurim, but
it really is not the first thing to be brought from the
new grain. The עומר Omer is, you know, the עומר Omer is
brought from the new grain but there's nothing you can do about
it. Nevertheless, what this ברייתא braita is saying is is that we
cannot undermine ביכורים bikurim more than that. So if we brought the
עומר Omer from the wheat, then there would be no way we
consider the שתי הלחם shtei halechem be first, the ביכורים, bikurim, because
there would already have been a wheat קרבן korban brought from the
from the עומר. Omer. So the עומר Omer have to be barley
to allow the שתי הלחם shtei halechem to be the first of
the wheat. Now, why is this a problem? So the so all
this ברייתא, braita, which is all discussing barley, the only relevance is
that it emphasizes the ביכורים bikurim status, excuse me, the שתי הלחם
shtei halechem status as ביכורים, bikurim, which means first, and therefore an
assumption that that word ביכורים bikurim is very central and required. Says
the גמרא Gemara says תיובתא, tiyufta, this is a contradiction. Now, what
contradiction is it? Because everybody before was saying how do we know
that the עומר Omer have to come from new grain? They had
other פסוקים: pesukim: ראשית קצירכם, reshis ketzirchem, first of the cutting, or
כרמל, karmel, moist, fresh. And here saying, ah, here we have an
idea first, but it's not learned out from ראשית reishis and it's
not learned out from כרמל, karmel, it's learned out from the word
ביכורים, bikurim, which is also a word by עומר. Omer. So therefore
it's a different פסוק. pasuk. Again, which is very strange. In the
end of the day, who cares? Everybody's agreed to the הלכה. halacha.
Why the גמרא Gemara is making such a big deal, I'll show
you a contradiction, and it uses the word תיובתא? tiyufta? These are
words that the גמרא Gemara usually uses when there's a real argument
of the הלכה, halacha, not just a question of which פסוק pasuk
you learn it out from. You'd like to think maybe, you know,
based on the פסוקים, pesukim, maybe it it somehow would impact how
do you define the concept of first, but the גמרא Gemara is
not spelling that out. Okay, so what what do we have here?
We have opinions that you can bring the עומר Omer from last
year's grain, which we saw yesterday, which is sort of an you
know the weight of the opinion, which is our משנה mishna and
which is the logic, that it had to be this year's grain,
either from the פסוק pasuk of ראשית reishit or קצירכם, ketzirchem, ראשית
reishis or כרמל karmel or ביכורים. bikurim. Now I do want to
discuss for a minute go back to the issue about bringing the
עומר Omer
on
שמיטה. shmita.
So one of the arguments that it could be last year's grain
is or else you're not fulfilling the demands of לאכלה. le'ochla. Presumably,
the response to that is, hey, you have no choice, you have
no choice. It's שמיטה, shmita, you got to bring it. Obviously this
is an exception. As תוספות Tosfos says, if we bring it on
שבת Shabbos and the תורה Torah allows it to override those considerations,
so it would override שמיטה shmita considerations, fine. But let's talk about
two other problems about the עומר Omer which we haven't explicitly addressed.
Number one is how can you cut it on the עומר? Omer?
You're not allowed to, right?
You're not allowed
to harvest on the עומר. Omer. You're not allowed to cut. So
you could say you could pick it, but says קצירכם, ketzirchem, it
would have to be harvested. So one answer תוספות Tosfos gives is
the same answer about how can you burn it? You got to
do what you got to do. The תורה Torah says bring it,
so it overrides these restrictions. The other answer תוספות Tosfos gives is
a little bit more interesting and is going to be relevant for
the other point I'm going to make, which is that he said
it's קצירכם, ketzirchem, you're not allowed to do private harvesting, you can
do this type of a communal harvesting for the sake of the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The reason I find that interesting is is
because it's not just like a technicality, right? Sometimes we have technicalities
and say oh this doesn't apply to the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash.
But by שמיטה, shmita, the primary concern of שמיטה shmita of harvesting,
why does it say שדך לא תקצור וכרמך לא תזמור sadcha lo
tikztor vecharmecha lo tizmor by שמיטה? shmita? Mostly תקצור, tikztor, excuse me.
What's the point? The point is that you're not supposed to be
exerting private ownership, right? Obviously it's not that you have to let
the stuff die on the vine, the עניים aniim come and they
eat it, and you also can pluck the stuff off and eat
it. The concern of the תורה Torah is not to exert private
ownership. Don't make it a year of harvest. So therefore, if the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash is coming and cutting some stuff down for
the עומר, Omer, it's not private ownership that it's exerting. So that
is like not just a technicality, it's really of a different nature
of harvesting and it doesn't violate the idea of שמיטה. shmita. That
also gets us to the next question, which is how are these
guys allowed to watch it? It says you pay them to watch
the עומר. Omer. But it but I mean this big תוספות Tosfos
is is based on the fact is is that you know there
are other sources that say you're not allowed to guard and protect
your field on שמיטה. shmita. That's part of the whole problem is
that you're not allowed to act like owners to protect your field.
So he has two similar answers: one answer he basically says is
that well they wouldn't exactly protect it. They would be standing there
and if somebody were to... come to pick it, they would say,
you should know we're planning on using this grain for the עומר.
Omer. And then the person would get the hint and not use
it, but they wouldn't lock the gates and keep them out. But
the other answer תוספות Tosafot says is no, is that that is
means that a private person to not protect his property, which is
an exertion of private ownership. But for the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash
to protect it, that would be, you know, that would be a
different type of an idea. That is sort of communal property, communal
for the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, it's not private. And again, the
final answer תוספות Tosafot gives, which is always the easy answer is:
you gotta bring the עומר, Omer, so you override all of these
things. But it's rather than just saying it's an override, I think
it's more interesting to think that this might be not the problems
of שמיטה Shemittah because the a lot of the problems with שמיטה
Shemittah are specifically the exerting of private ownership. Okay, so that is
the עומר Omer coming on שמיטה Shemittah and how and whether the
עומר Omer can come from this year or last year's, and different
פסוקים pesukim that might be the basis of it. Now we go
on to a slightly different topic. תנן התם. Tnan hatam. We taught
over there in בכורים Bikkurim the following: אין מביאין בכורים חוץ משבעת
המינים. Ein mevi'in bikkurim chutz mishivat haminim. בכורים Bikkurim only come from
the seven species: חיטה, שעורה, גפן, תאנה, chittah, se'orah, gefen, te'enah, etc.
The seven things that ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael is praised with, by
the way,
דבש devash honey, considered to be דבש תמרים, devash temarim, date honey,
because it's considered to be referring to agricultural product.
ולו, Velo, now, although it's for those seven,
but even within those seven, ולא מתמרים שבהרים, velo mitmarim shebeharim, not
from dates that grow up on the mountain tops. You know, I
guess יריחו Yericho is עיר התמרים Ir HaTemarim and we decided a
while ago that it was in a valley, right? So it spoke
before about them being in valleys. I don't know. Presumably, the date,
the palm trees on mountain tops, the stuff is not as good.
ולא מפירות שבעמקים, Velo miperot shebe'amakim, and also not other fruit that
grow in the valleys. So for some reason, dates are bad on
the mountain tops, and other fruit is bad in the valley. The
assumption here is, although not stated, that this is grade B produce.
Okay, so you don't bring it from the type of fruits that
are not the best of the fruits. Now it's interesting for a
moment to contrast to our משנה. mishnah. Remember our משנה mishnah says
that you bring it from וכולם אין באים אלא מן המובחר שלהם,
vekulam ein ba'im ela min hamuvchar shelahem, that you also you bring
the grain, you know, the grain for the מנחה minchah particularly for
the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, you use the
choice grains, you use the choice flour. It said the alpha grain
is this and the second grain is that. Now again, the sense,
although the משנה mishnah did use the language אין באים אלא מן
המובחר, ein ba'im ela min hamuvchar, you only use choice flour for
the מנחה, minchah, probably, at least my intuition would be that that's
לכתחילה. lechatchilah. בדיעבד, Bedi'avad, it would be okay. Now we're going to
have, so now we're saying something parallel by בכורים, Bikkurim, and we're
going to have an interesting discussion: is the idea of using the
best and the choice, is that a לכתחילה lechatchilah or even a
בדיעבד? bedi'avad? And by בכורים, Bikkurim, it's, you know, there's more reason
to think it's בדיעבד bedi'avad because the whole idea of בכורים, Bikkurim,
well, you know, you could say it's first, first no matter what
the quality is, but you could also understand the conceptual idea of
first, you know, also as a conceptually also an idea of best.
And that therefore if it was not the best, maybe it's not
not good even בדיעבד. bedi'avad. So that's going to be the discussion
right now. So let's take a look.
אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, so עולא Ulla says: אם הביא, לא קידש.
Im hevi, lo kidesh. If you absolutely brought בכורים Bikkurim from these
grade B fruits, they do not become sanctified as בכורים; Bikkurim; you're
not, it's not בכורים. Bikkurim. בכורים Bikkurim have to be from only
the grade A fruits. יתיב רבה וקאמר להאי שמעתא. Yativ Rabbah veka'amar
lehai shema'ata. So רבה Rabbah was sitting over was sitting and telling
over this discussion and that עולא's Ulla position that it doesn't work
even בדיעבד. bedi'avad. איתיביה רב אחא בר אבא לרבה. Eitiveih Rav Acha
bar Abba leRabbah. So רב אחא בר אבא Rav Acha bar Abba
asked רבה: Rabbah: how could עולא Ulla say such a thing? קרבן
ראשית שתהא ראשית לכל המנחות. Korban reshit shete'reshit lechol hamenachot. So here's
a ברייתא. braita. That they will see the question is going to
come, we have to go through a lot of the ברייתא braita
to get to the question. Okay? So it says:
קרבן ראשית תקריבו אותם לה' ואל המזבח לא יעלו לריח ניחוח. Korban
reshit takrivu otam l'Hashem v'el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu lere'ach nicho'ach. So that's
talking about the עומר Omer and the בכורים, Bikkurim, that they are
a ראשית, reshit, but they don't get put on the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. Well the עומר Omer does, but on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Excuse me, but anyway, the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם, Shtei
HaLechem, בכורים Bikkurim and the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. So קרבן ראשית
שתהא ראשית לכל המנחות. Korban reshit shete'reshit lechol hamenachot. It will be
the first of all the מנחות. menachot. This is talking about about
the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. וכן הוא אומר: בהקריבכם מנחה חדשה לה'
בשבועותיכם. Vechen hu omer: behakrivchem minchah chadashah l'Hashem beshavu'oteichem. When you bring
the new מנחה minchah on your שבועות. Shavuot. So this is so
here, very apropos of שבועות. Shavuot. So when you bring the שתי
הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. So here it's called a מנחה חדשה, minchah chadashah,
there it was called a קרבן ראשית. korban reshit. So we're assuming
that we're talking here about the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. And the
שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem is the first of all the מנחות. menachot.
What does it mean the first? It is the first מנחה minchah
that comes from the new grain, parenthesis, other than the עומר. Omer.
Okay, but it is the first מנחה minchah of the new grain,
that's the קרבן ראשית. korban reshit. אין לי אלא חדשה של חיטין.
Ein li ela chadashah shel chittin. Now it's going to ask that.
I only know that it is the first מנחה minchah of the
of the new wheat grain. חדשה של... Chadashah shel... מנין, minayin, how
do
I
know? תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar חדשה, chadashah, חדשה. chadashah. It says חדשה
chadashah twice. It says, what does it say? וביום הביכורים בהקריבכם מנחה
חדשה לה' בשבעתיכם. Uveyom habikkurim behakrivchem mincha chadashah l'Hashem beshavuoteichem.
Do you have a פסוק? pasuk? Do you have a חומש Chumash
out there?
Port it up on your side, Eli. What edition do you have,
Eli?
It's by the... Steinsaltz. Steinsaltz. Steinsaltz. וביום הביכורים בהקריבכם מנחה חדשה לה'
בשבעתיכם, Uveyom habikkurim behakrivchem mincha chadashah l'Hashem beshavuoteichem, והקרבתם מנחה חדשה לה'.
vehekravtem mincha chadashah l'Hashem.
So there it
says חדשה chadashah twice.
No, maybe it says חדשה chadashah back there by
קרבן ראשית. korban reshis. תקריבו אותם לה', takrivu osam l'Hashem, ואל המזבח
לא יעלו לריח ניחוח. ve'el hamizbe'ach lo ya'alu lere'ach nicho'ach. Hold on,
let's take a look.
וביום הביכורים, Uveyom habikkurim, yeah, so it says וביום הביכורים בהקריבכם מנחה
חדשה לה' בשבעתיכם. Uveyom habikkurim behakrivchem mincha chadashah l'Hashem beshavuoteichem.
So there's one. Oh, and when it says about counting, meaning in
במדבר, Bamidbar, and then when it says by אמור, Emor, right, but
it says by אמור Emor by counting, then it says you count
שבע שבועות sheva shavuos and you bring a מנחה חדשה. mincha chadashah.
Okay, so it says חדשה chadashah twice by ביכורים. bikkurim. אם אינו
עניין לחדשה של חטים, Im eino inyan lachadashah shel chittin, you don't
need it to tell me the first point, that it's the first
new קרבן korban of wheat, because that we learned from the first
חדשה, chadashah, תנהו עניין לחדשה של שעורים, teneihu inyan lachadashah shel se'orim,
that it even is the first מנחה mincha from barley, parentheses again
with the exception of the עומר, Omer, which you got to bring.
But anyway, other than the עומר, Omer, so again, people can get
this mixed up because the עומר Omer is barley and the שתי
הלחם shetei halechem is wheat. They might think the עומר Omer worked
for barley and the שתי הלחם shetei halechem worked for wheat. That's
not the way it works. The עומר Omer works for outside the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, it allows all the new grain, whether barley,
wheat, whatever outside the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. The שתי הלחם shetei
halechem works in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. It allows the new
grain in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, but also whether wheat or
barley, whatever. So although the עומר Omer is from barley, nothing else
of the new grain can be put on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, even
barley, until you bring the שתי הלחם. shetei halechem.
Okay, so that's what we learned from חדשה. chadashah. Now,
ומנין שלא תקדם לביכורים, Uminayin shelo takdem l'bikkurim, how do you know
that you cannot bring ביכורים bikkurim before you bring the שתי הלחם?
shetei halechem? They have to be the very first stuff of the
new produce, not just the new grain, but even of the new
fruit. And it's interesting because of course ביכורים bikkurim was not put
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. Of course, the שתי הלחם shetei halechem isn't
put on the מזבח mizbe'ach either. You know, the שתי הלחם shetei
halechem comes with the lambs, they're חמץ, chametz, they don't get put
on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. But anyway, how do you know that before
the שתי הלחם shetei halechem you cannot even bring ביכורים? bikkurim? תלמוד
לומר, Talmud lomar, וחג שבועות תעשה לך ביכורי קציר חטים. Vechag Shavuos
ta'aseh lecha bikkurei ketzir chittin. You shall have a חג השבועות Chag
Hashavuos of the ביכורי, bikkurei, the first of the harvesting of your
wheat. So with because of the use of the word ביכורי, bikkurei,
it's telling you that this has to be the very first. Even
prior to ביכורים, bikkurim, only first comes the שתי הלחם, shetei halechem,
then come the ביכורים. bikkurim. אין לי אלא ביכורי הקציר. Ein li
ela bikkurei hakatzir.
Do I get that it's the very first of the cutting, of
the harvesting? So it has to come before ביכורים bikkurim of wheat.
But ביכורי מעשיך, bikkurei ma'asecha, but ביכורי קציר, bikkurei ketzir, whatever, ביכורי
קציר חטים, bikkurei ketzir chittin, קציר שעורים
מנין? ketzir se'orim minayin? How do I know that again this is
not bringing a מנחה mincha of שעורים, se'orim, that we already established,
but how do I know you can't bring ביכורים bikkurim of barley?
Right, because again, the difference is a מנחה mincha is put on
the מזבח, mizbe'ach, ביכורים bikkurim is just presented. So how do I
know that you cannot bring ביכורים bikkurim of barley prior to the
שתי הלחם? shetei halechem? תלמוד לומר, Talmud lomar, וחג הקציר ביכורי מעשיך
אשר תזרע בשדה. Vechag hakatzir bikkurei ma'asecha asher tizra basadeh. And how
is שבועות Shavuos described? שבועות Shavuos is described as the holiday of
harvesting, the ביכורים bikkurim of all of your, you know, action, of
all of your labor. So therefore again, שבועות Shavuos is the holiday
you bring the שתי הלחם. shetei halechem. שתי הלחם Shetei halechem is
called ביכורים bikkurim and it's called ביכורים bikkurim of the very first
of all of the things that you plant, which means that anything
that you plant cannot come prior to the שתי הלחם. shetei halechem.
So whether it's as a מנחה mincha or whether it's ביכורים, bikkurim,
the שתי הלחם shetei halechem has to be the very first. Okay,
so what?
אשר תזרע בשדה. Asher tizra basadeh. Anything you harvest too, but it's
ביכורי... bikkurei... but here the emphasis: מעשיך אשר תזרע בשדה. ma'asecha asher
tizra basadeh. Not limiting itself to wheat, but anything that you labor
and that you plant, for all of those things, right, the שתי
הלחם shetei halechem has to be first. No
מנחה mincha can come before that, no ביכורים bikkurim can come before
that. But we're not done. Because תזרע tizra means from the word
seed, you plant seeds. There are things that grow that you could
bring as ביכורים bikkurim that don't come from the planting of seeds,
from sowing. What are those? ואין לי אלא שתזרע. Ve'ein li ela
shetizra. I only know that they have to... that the שתי הלחם
shetei halechem has to be first from things that you planted.
שעלו מאליהן מנין, She'alu me'alehen minayin, how about... Things that rose under
their own, תלמוד לומר בשדה, Talmud lomar ba-sadeh, no, anything that comes
from the field. Alright, so that covers all grain products. But then
it says, ואין לי אלא בשדה, ve-ein li ela ba-sadeh, I only
know that the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem has to be the first
of things that come from the field.
מניין לרבות שבגג ושבחורבה ושבאתיס ושבצינה? minayin lerabbos she-ba-gag ve-she-ba-churva ve-she-ba-atis ve-she-ba-tzina?
How do I know things that grow not exactly on a field,
things that grow on a rooftop garden, or in a חורבה churva
which is like, you know, a sort of a desolate yard, so
it's not really planted, you wouldn't really call it like a, you
know, a plowed field, and אתיס atis or grew in a flowerpot
or a pot, flowerpot or a pot, how do I know even
if it doesn't grow in a field?
תלמוד לומר בכורי כל אשר בארצם, Talmud lomar bikkurei kol asher be-artzam,
because there's another פסוק pasuk that's when it speaks about what the
כהנים kohanim get, it says the first fruit of all that is
in their land. So you see that the word ביכורים bikkurim refers
to in reference to not just things that are planted but ביכורים
bikkurim means in reference to everything that grows, even if it's not
growing בשדה. ba-sadeh. Then it says, מניין שתי קודמת לנסכים ופירות האילן?
minayin shtei kodemes le-nesachim u-peiros ha-ilan? That for me would have been
the first question. Until now it's always אשר תזרע בשדה. asher tizra
ba-sadeh. The idea of זרע zera seeds, sowing, and שדה sadeh a
field, I mean the field of harvesting refers to grain. How do
you know that the concept of the ביכורים bikkurim and that really
also conceptually you would think that the ideas relating to harvesting are
not related to the ideas of the ripening of the fruit? So
I get that I can't bring wheat and barley ביכורים bikkurim until
I've brought my שתי הלחם. shtei ha-lechem. שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem is
about the קציר katzir the harvest. But how do I know that
the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem has to come before I even bring
new fruit? Maybe it's completely unrelated to the fruit? So how do
I know that? And the wine, you know, wine which is coming
from the grapes, that that has to wait till the שתי הלחם?
shtei ha-lechem? So it says, so it ends by saying, נאמר כאן
בכורי מעשיך, ne-emar kan bikkurei ma-asecha, so here it says that the
שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem is the first of your, of your, of
your labors, ונאמר להלן ve-ne-emar la-halan and it says by סוכות, Sukkos,
באספך מעשיך מן השדה be-aspecha ma-asecha min ha-sadeh when you gather in
your labors from the field. מה להלן נסכים ופירות האילן, mah la-halan
nesachim u-peiros ha-ilan, so therefore it's talking about, you know, not literally
נסכים, nesachim, grapes, things you'll make wine out of and fruit, because
when the holiday of harvest, סוכות, Sukkos, refers to all things, grain
and fruit and all things, אף כאן נסכים ופירות האילן af kan
nesachim u-peiros ha-ilan here when it says the first of your labors,
labors is a category we see elsewhere that refers to all your
agricultural labors, everything you do, not just the harvesting, not just the
planting, you know, the wheat and the grain and so on, but
anything that you labor which includes all fruit and so on. Okay,
so that is a, so that's the point of the ברייתא. braisa.
What's the upshot of this whole ברייתא? braisa?
The same way we had a whole ברייתא braisa with a lot
of פסוקים pesukim before that told us one basic הלכה halacha which
was the עומר omer comes from barley, here this whole ברייתא braisa
is telling us one basic הלכה halacha which is you cannot bring
anything new from the new fruit or the new grain to the
בית המקדש Beis ha-Mikdash until the שתי הלחם. shtei ha-lechem. Whether you're
bringing it as a מנחה mincha and whether you're bringing it from
barley, doesn't matter, can't come before. Even if it's not, whether you're
bringing it as ביכורים bikkurim and it's grain, so can't bring before.
But not only can you not bring grain before because you understand
at least the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem is the, you know, first
harvest, the first קרבן korban of the new grain, but now the
last point is it's also the first of בכורי מעשיך. bikkurei ma-asecha.
It is the first of all of your labors that is being
becoming ripened and therefore before the שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem is brought
to represent the first of all of your labors, you cannot bring
any other thing from the new, from the new produce, even whether
it's grain or whether it's fruit. Okay, so that's the role of
the שתי הלחם. shtei ha-lechem. It's interesting because, you know, again שבועות
Shavuos is coming up and in order to make שבועות Shavuos meaningful
for us we always, you know, transpose the meaning to be talking
about מתן תורה Matan Torah and stay up all night learning תורה.
Torah. And here for once we're actually getting an opportunity to reflect
on, you know, the more biblical significance of שבועות Shavuos and the
שתי הלחם, shtei ha-lechem, which
we are less in touch with, which is this whole idea of
representing the first of our labors. You know, so to some degree
you have a little bit about it about the עומר, omer, but,
you know, the emphasis is that שבועות Shavuos is חג הביכורים chag
ha-bikkurim and the whole process of then afterwards bringing ביכורים bikkurim and
all of that comes after שבועות. Shavuos. But שבועות Shavuos represents the
first expression of that, you know, of the gratitude and of the
work that we've been doing but seeing God's hand in it and
so on. So something to be thinking about as שבועות Shavuos comes
around.
Call it the first and the ב? Beis? But the first is
very tiny, very...
so that is interesting, you know, why we're going to assume and
that's what we're going to turn to right now, this question about
what happens if you bring it from grade B fruit. Now the
grade B idea, like remember it started with the discussion about the
palm trees and the mountains which is what we're getting to. But
the idea of even there about grade B is,
is it of the type of, you know, the the species, that's
probably the wrong word, that, you know, has to be like the
the ב... Beis... the better, so stuff that grows on the, you
know, dates that grow in the valley are better than grade B
dates that grow on the mountain tops? But then there's a question
of the specific one that I am bringing, and there you're actually,
you know, again, I'm not a farmer, I don't know, but I
was guessing the same thing that you were saying, that it could
be that the stuff that ripens first is not necessarily going to
be the best of what I have to select from. So that
is true.
But it is the best in terms of our faith, in terms
of the fact that ברוך השם Baruch Hashem that we didn't when
you plant, you don't know whether something's going to hit. So here,
that's part of
of the relationship between you and Hashem, that here it is.
Ah, that's a very beautiful idea. Also the idea, thank you, of
course, that there's a concept that runs right through the whole תורה
Torah of like the idea of בכור Bechor in בראשית Bereishit
is always given preference
for what is really the best as it's not what is... the
idea of בכור Bechor in בראשית Bereishit and בכור Bechor in משפטים,
Mishpatim, right,
even with people, right, there's the...
but there's also the פדיון Pidyon of a human בכור, Bechor,
right, which is also coming up in the פרשיות. Parashiyos. Yeah, absolutely,
absolutely. Okay, so we have two good שיעורים Shiurim for שבועות Shavuos
night now to talk about both those topics. Let's finish the גמרא.
Gemara. Why is the גמרא Gemara quoting all of this?
What? I know what you're going to say, and you go, yeah,
right.
So why is the... so what is the... so why is the
גמרא Gemara quoting all this to tell to get to the following
point. תני מיהא, Tani Miha, so we taught nonetheless, meaning okay, that
was a fascinating ברייתא, Bereisa, but let's get to the point.
What line interests us? שגג כבכור ושבעציץ ושבספינה. Shebegag Kebechor Veshebeatzitz Veshebesfina.
It says, how do I know that
the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem has to come before stuff that even
didn't grow in the field, that grew on a rooftop or grew
on a boat? So it says no, it has to come before
that. But what do you learn from that? You learn that after
you bring the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, you can bring ביכורים Bikkurim
from stuff that grew on the rooftop or on the boat. So
it basically is assuming that has to be at least as good
quality as the תמרים Tamarim on the mountaintops, okay? This is not
growing in ideal conditions. So here it says it's just telling you
you have to wait for the שתי הלחם, Shtei HaLechem, but it's
implying that you can still bring the ביכורים Bikkurim from this type
of produce.
I don't see why this is inferior quality. You know, there's one
is too high, maybe the air is too thin or something? Right,
I don't know, still, you know, still sea level.
Yeah, but it's not
growing straight from the ground. I mean, it's growing from some dirt
you have in a boat. So I can see it. I don't
know, I'm not a farmer. The גמרא Gemara knew a lot more
about agriculture than I do. So the גמרא... Gemara... maybe could answer
that, but it's assuming that that can't be worse quality than the
תמרים Tamarim on the mountains. So it says, so how... could you
see you can bring ביכורים Bikkurim from that? So the גמרא Gemara
says, סיפא אף מן המנחות. Seifa Af Min Hamenachos. No, no, no,
because remember ביכורים Bikkurim has to... the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem has
to be the first of... before ביכורים Bikkurim and before מנחות חדשות.
Minchos Chadashos. So when it's saying how do I know it has
to precede even stuff that grew in a boat or on a
roof, it's talking about using that grain for a מנחה. Mincha. For
ביכורים Bikkurim it wouldn't be good, for a מנחה Mincha it would
be good. Now again by the way, note, it's quite interesting, it's
almost in quiet conversation with our משנה Mishnah but not being explicit
because our משנה Mishnah said that a מנחה Mincha has to come
from quality grain. But here it's basically implicitly admitting, and by focusing
on ביכורים Bikkurim it was already implicitly admitted that that would not
be בדיעבד. Bediavad. Nobody is suggesting that a מנחה Mincha from inferior
quality grain is not good בדיעבד. Bediavad. The question is by ביכורים.
Bikkurim. So here when we have this problem, ah you see it
can come from stuff on a boat, we say no no, it's
a מנחה Mincha can come from stuff on a boat, not the
ביכור. Bikkur. Okay, so let's take a look.
But after... it was like, you know, getting the three סאה Se'ah
of the flour, sifting it through like thirteen times and everything, had
to actually even be that good grain? So what's the whole...
Possibly לכתחילה Lechatchila בדיעבד. Bediavad.
Now again there's also the whole question about whether you're talking about
the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם Shtei HaLechem and communal sacrifices
versus private, but our משנה Mishnah seemed to be talking at least
about the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם. Shtei HaLechem. But again
our משנה Mishnah says it was it was required. What I just
think is interesting is the גמרא Gemara by... we're going to I
think believe me I learned until the next משנה, Mishnah, it's not
going to discuss that line, you know, that line in the משנה.
Mishnah. It's not going to tell you whether that is בדיעבד Bediavad
or not. But I think it's implicit from this discussion that it's
assuming that it at most it'll be בדיעבד Bediavad by ביכורים, Bikkurim,
not by... so that's what it says here. It says that okay,
there where it says you can get some from stuff on the
boat, that's for a מנחה, Mincha, not for ביכור. Bikkur. מכדי דתנן.
Michdi Deatnan. What idea... We know, right, and again right. Okay so
מתקיף לה רב אדא בר אהבה. Matkif La Rav Adda bar Ahava.
So רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar Ahava asked on this.
אי הכי היינו דכתיב. I Hachi Hainu Dechtiv. We're well we're talking
about מנחה? Mincha? How do you explain the פסוק? Pasuk? You're dealing
with this whole פסוק Pasuk over there in קרח Korach which says
you know, בהקריבכם מנחה חדשה. Behakrivchem Mincha Chadasha. So it also says
there כל טהור בביתך יאכל אתה, Kol Tahor Beveitcha Yochal Otah,
that every pure person in your house can eat it, יאכל אתו.
Yochal Oto. This is all פסוק Pasuk we were דרשנ'ן darshaning where
it speaks about מנחה חדשה. Mincha Chadasha. So if every pure person
in your house means not only the men... But even the wives,
right, and the children and so on and the girls, so therefore
we can't be talking about a מנחה. mincha. מנחה mincha is only
eaten by male כהנים. kohanim. So if we're דרשנינג darshaning this פסוק,
pasuk, this פסוק, pasuk, which says it has to be the new,
you know, and this sort of relative to the other stuff, so
we're talking about relative to בכורים, bikkurim, not relative to מנחה. mincha.
וכי מנחה מנחות לזכרי כהונה הוא דמיתאכלן, v'chi mincha menachot l'zichrei kehuna
hu d'mita'chlen, but מנחות menachot are eaten by male כהנים. kohanim.
So it's not eaten by by everybody in the house. אמר רב
משארשיא תרי קראי כתיבי. amar Rav Mesharshia trei k'raei ksivei. There are
two פסוקים. psukim. וחיה, v'chaya, וכתיב כל טהור בביתך יאכל אותה. u'chsiv
kol tahor b'veitcha yochal ota. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? Let me read
it so that we have the full context.
It says like this, this is in the list at the end
of קרח Korach of all of the things that God is, you
know, promised, given, reaffirmed that go to the כהנים kohanim after their
position had been challenged. So it says like this, בכורי כל אשר
בארצם אשר יביאו לה' לך יהיה,
bikkurei
kol
asher b'artzam asher yavi'u l'Hashem lach yiheye,
the first of all of their in their land that they bring
to God, so will be to you, כל טהור בביתך יאכלנו, kol
tahor b'veitcha yochlenu,
everybody pure in your house will eat it. So the לך יהיה,
lach yiheye, right, is is on the one hand saying to you,
which the גמרא Gemara here understands means more limited to you, the
male כהנים kohanim who I'm talking to, and כל טהור בביתך kol
tahor b'veitcha is more inclusive. So it's going to say ויאכל אותו.
v'yochal oto. כל טהור בביתך, kol tahor b'veitcha, did I miss יאכלנו?
yochlenu? It says here יאכל אותה. yochal ota.
They probably fixed it on the side. Yeah, they fixed it on
the side. Okay, on the ה. he. Okay. So anyway you have
two פסוקים. psukim. הא כיצד? ha keitzad? How do you satisfy both
פסוקים? psukim? כאן בבכורים כאן במנחות. kan b'bikkurim kan b'menachot.
Where it says לך יהיה, lach yiheye, it's talking about the בכורים,
bikkurim, excuse me, talking about the מנחות, menachot, which is only to
you the male כהנים. kohanim. Where it says כל טהור בביתך, kol
tahor b'veitcha, that's talking about the בכורים. bikkurim. So what we are
saying is that this פסוק pasuk here says that they get the
first, which which is here meant first of what? So we're now
saying it's not just first of before the בכורים, bikkurim, but it
also means first before the מנחות. menachot. And you get that which
is first relative to בכורים, bikkurim, relative to the מנחות, menachot, but
we're talking about both, it has to precede both, and therefore since
we're talking both about בכורים bikkurim and מנחות, menachot, when we talk
about stuff that's coming from the ship and so on, we could
be talking about מנחות menachot and not about בכורים. bikkurim. So that's
answer number one. Okay, let's, what have we said? This ברייתא baraita
says the שתי הלחם shtei halechem has to precede בכורים, bikkurim, it
even has to precede stuff that grew on ships and on rooftops.
So we're saying doesn't that show בכורים bikkurim can come from ships
and rooftops? It says no. Maybe that's talking about מנחות menachot because
it also has to precede מנחות. menachot. And maybe maybe that comes
from ships and rooftops but not בכורים. bikkurim. So the גמרא Gemara
is not done. רב פפא אמר כולה במנחות. Rav Papa amar kula
b'menachot. Actually this whole פסוק pasuk means that it is the first
relative to מנחות, menachot, not the first relative to בכורים. bikkurim. So
what do you do about כל טהור בביתך, kol tahor b'veitcha, everybody
in your house? So he
says וסיפא דקרא אתיא ללחמי תודה. v'seifa d'kra atya l'lachmei toda. Ah,
the bread of the תודה. toda. Remember that? In my mind that
was always a questionable מנחה, mincha, but the גמרא Gemara assumes that
that is a מנחה. mincha. But it's very bizarre because מנחות menachot
are קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim and are only eaten by male כהנים.
kohanim. The bread of a תודה toda is קדשים קלים, kodashim kalim,
it's eaten by the owners. It's except for the four breads that
are given to the כהנים. kohanim. How are those treated? Those are
treated like תרומה, truma, they can be eaten by not only כהנים
kohanim but by כהנים kohanim families as well. So therefore this פסוק
pasuk that says that it gets, it's eaten by everybody in your
house is talking about מנחות, menachot, but a certain type of מנחה,
mincha, the bread that comes with the תודה toda that can be
eaten by all the members of the household. So again what we
in order to get out of this problem that this ברייתא baraita
sounds like it says the שתי הלחם shtei halechem has to precede
even stuff that grew on the rooftops, so it said, ah, it
seems like בכורים bikkurim grows on rooftops, it says no, it means
the מנחות menachot that grow on rooftops. How do you fit it
in the פסוקים psukim that say that we're trying to say this
פסוק pasuk of ראשית בכורי, reshit bikkurei, what is the פסוק pasuk
again?
בכורי כל אשר בארצם אשר יביאו לה', bikkurei kol asher b'artzam asher
yavi'u l'Hashem, first of everything, which we we said means first relative
to the other stuff. So we're saying no, the relative to the
other stuff includes even מנחות. menachot. And the fact that it speaks
about eating it, everybody eating it in your house, here we're saying
could mean about the לחמי תודה. lachmei toda. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara restates this debate בפלוגתא. b'plugta. This issue about בכורים bikkurim
coming from the non-choice stuff is a debate. רבי יוחנן אמר אם
הביא לא קידש. Rabbi Yochanan amar im hevi lo kidesh. If you
brought בכורים bikkurim from the stuff that grew on the, you
know, mountain, mountaintops or the rooftops, it's not בכורים. bikkurim. ריש לקיש
אמר אם הביא קידש. Reish Lakish amar im hevi kidesh. No, if
you bring it it is בכורים. bikkurim. It's maybe it's בדיעבד, b'di'avad,
but if you bring it it's בכורים. bikkurim. And look at the
nice analogy he makes. נעשה ככחוש בקדשים. na'aseh k'kachush b'kodashim. He says
let's say you take a קרבן korban that's skinny and scrawny and
so on and you sanctify it. So it's not an ideal קרבן,
korban, but nobody says it's not valid. So you know, so... Therefore,
obviously ideally you're supposed to get the best of everything, but בדיעבד
bedi'avad *B'dieved* it works. And again presumably if it works by קרבן
*korban* going back to our point, it also works by the flour
for the מנחות Menachot, *menachot*. The only issue that's being debated here
is not animals, is not flour, the only issue being debated is
ביכורים Bikurim. *Bikkurim*. Does ביכורים Bikurim. *Bikkurim* have to be from the
best? So let's see what רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan, *Rabbi Yochanan's* response
is.
Where are we? נעשה ככחוש בקדשים *Na'aseh k'kachush b'kodshim*.
בשלמא ריש לקיש Bishlama Reish Lakish, *Bishlama Reish Lakish*, so the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says as I understand ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish*
כי דאמר טעמא *ki d'amar ta'ama*. He gives his reason. Okay, it's
not ideal, but it's still good. אלא רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan מאי
טעמא *Ela Rabbi Yochanan mai ta'ama*? What's רבי יוחנן's *Rabbi Yochanan's* reason
that ביכורים Bikurim, *Bikkurim* if it's not ideal is not good? דאמר
רבי אלעזר רבי יוחנן חזאי בחלום *D'amar Rabbi Elazar: Rabbi Yochanan chazai
b'chalom* or בחלמא *b'chelma*. So רבי אלעזר *Rabbi Elazar* said I saw
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* in the dream. Okay, so this is after
by the way, though here the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is trying to
explain רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*, by the way after his death, which
is not a חידוש *chiddush*, but I gotta tell you for people
that spend a lot of time learning גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, when you
get to the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says what would רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* say? רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* would say this and ריש לקיש
Reish Lakish *Reish Lakish* says that, and pretty soon you're forgetting that
the גמרא *Gemara* is speculating on how they would answer back and
forth and you're imagining that they really were saying those things back
and forth as opposed to what almost always is the case that
the גמרא *Gemara* takes their positions and then imagines how they would
respond to different arguments. So here the גמרא *Gemara* is sort of
making it very clear what would רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* say and
now we're making it very explicit. רבי יוחנן's *Rabbi Yochanan's* already dead,
right? רבי אלעזר's *Rabbi Elazar's* saying, you know what? I saw רבי
יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* in the dream. Now you would say maybe and
רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* maybe told me this in a dream, but
actually no, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says because I saw him in a
dream, that inspired me or that gave me this סיעתא דשמיא *siyata
d'shmaya* to come to his defense. So nobody's actually claiming that he
was given the answer by רבי יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan*. Okay, so let's
see what it says.
מילתא מעלייתא אמינא *Milsa ma'alya amina*.
So I will say, notice a good answer for רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan*, a good idea. אמר קרא *Amar kra*, the פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
says מראשית *Mei-reishis*. It says you shall bring from the first, מראשית
כל פרי האדמה תביא מארצך Me'artzecha, *mei-reishis kol pri ha-adamah tavi mei-artzecha*.
Okay, so from the first, ולא כל ראשית *v'lo kol reishis*, not
all the first. Now that we're assuming is not yet our point,
that we're assuming maybe is excluding for example non-שבעת המינים *shiv'as haminim*,
only from the first, not everything but some of them, only from
the שבעת המינים *shiv'as haminim*. מארצך *Mei-artzecha*, this is the point, ולא
כל ארצך *v'lo kol artzecha*, not anywhere on your land. Meaning so
if it's growing on non-choice land and this by the way might
go as I think part of the point which it's not just,
you know again and also Bobby, it's not just that the ביכורים
Bikurim *Bikkurim* itself is the best, it might be the thing you
pick is not the best, but what we're at least saying is
it has to be growing, you know, from stuff that grew in
the choicest location, in the location that is most ideal or that
is ideal for its growth. So therefore if palm trees grow up
on the mountains, there are other things grow in the valleys, the
things that grow on rooftops or boats, they're not growing in ideal
conditions. So that's his emphasis. Not about the quality of the fruit,
but whether they have come from the best of the land, have
they come from, you know, growing in ideal conditions? Like hydroponics, yeah
exactly.
I'm just curious for a second going back a little bit. What
did he even actually say that רבי יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* in my dream said to me? Right, that's carrying on very
dangerous.
Right, and I didn't say
that. There are a few places in the גמרא *Gemara* where somebody
appears in a dream and sort of actually communicates very specific information
and I'm not sure how much it is often it's more of
an agadic thing. I'm not sure how much that occurs within halachic
discourse, like
here's the answer he gave me to this question in the dream.
Yeah, I
listen
and all this begins to look wholesome.
I know, I know, but that's not what we're saying here. All
right, so at least we don't have to worry about it now.
Okay, so anyways, let's see. That's what he says. ולא כל ארצך
*V'lo kol artzecha*. וריש לקיש האי ארצך מאי עביד ליה *V'Reish Lakish
hai artzecha mai avid leh*? What does he do with that, which
seems to limit not every place on the land? So מבעי ליה
לכדתניא *mib'ei leh l'cheid'tanya* for what the ברייתא braita *braita* says. בנייה
בר רבי אומר *B'niyei bar Rebbi omer*, נאמר כאן ארץ ונאמר להלן
ארץ *ne'emar kan aretz v'ne'emar l'hallan aretz*. It says here ארץ *aretz*
and it says over there ארץ *aretz*, which is ארץ חטה ושעורה
וגפן ותאנה ורמון *eretz chita u-se'orah v'gefen u-se'einah v'rimon*. It covers the
שבעת המינים *shiv'as haminim*. So נאמר להלן ארץ *ne'emar l'hallan aretz*, מה
להלן שבח הארץ *mah l'hallan shvach ha-aretz*, the best meaning again, but
they're talking about שבעת המינים *shiv'as haminim*, not exactly where they grew
or anything, but which type of fruit, the best, the שבעת המינים
*shiv'as haminim*. אף כאן שבח הארץ *Af kan shvach ha-aretz*, so here
too by ביכורים Bikurim *Bikkurim* it's the שבעת המינים *shiv'as haminim*. Now
of course that's a little complicated because then the גמרא *Gemara* sort
of says so what do you do from some you know the
other פסוק *pasuk* of מראשית *mei-reishis*. If מראשית *mei-reishis* we had said
before meant to tell you שבעת המינים *shiv'as haminim* and the גמרא
*Gemara* yeah I don't know the גמרא *Gemara*'s not dealing with that.
Okay, somehow we got out of our problem. So ואידך *v'idach*, what
would ריש לקיש Reish Lakish, *Reish Lakish* say? ארץ מארץ *Aretz mei-aretz*.
No, I get it from the מ' *mem*, מארץ *mei-aretz* means not
all the place, only from the ideal growing environment. ואידך ארץ מארץ
לא משמע ליה *V'idach aretz mei-aretz lo mashma leh*, he's not you
know he's not dealing with that. not impressed by that. Okay. So
here we have the debate and we finally have the פסוק for
ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish מארצך, which means from the best place of
the land, the place that's most ideal for this growing. But again,
what's also very clear is if we're going to say this, this
is not רבי יוחנן, if we're going to say it, we're going
to say it by ביכורים. Bikurim We're not going to say it
by קרבנות, Korbanot, by animals, and implicitly, I think it's in conversation
with our משנה, mishnah, we're not going to say it by מנחות,
there בדיעבד non-choice is okay, but maybe by ביכורים. Bikurim And again,
also notice by ביכורים, Bikurim? we don't just mean that this fruit
is a scrawny fruit. What we're actually saying is it's growing in
an wrong place. It's not representative of the best of the land
because it's not growing in the place that is ideal for it.
Okay, so let's just look at a little bit more on this.
Okay, תני חדא. Tani chada. So we have one ברייתא braita that
says
שבגג ושבחורבה שבעציץ ושבספינה. shebe-gag ve-she-be-churba shebe-atzitz ve-shebe-sfina. If it grew on
the rooftop,
the vacant field, in a flowerpot and on a boat, מביא וקורא,
mevi ve-kore, you bring ביכורים Bikurim and you actually make the declaration,
which means that you are really fully biblically obligated to bring ביכורים
and you say, you know, whenever it says קורא, kore, which is
the what the פסוק says that you say when you bring it,
ארמי אובד אבי Arami oved avi and so on, that reflects the
idea that you are biblically—it is a biblical
obligation. ותניא אידך, Ve-tanya idach, we have another ברייתא braita that says
מביא ואינו קורא. mevi ve-eino kore. If you bring from those places,
you bring it but you don't make the declaration, which usually means
that it's not biblical, it was only rabbinic. So here we have
one ברייתא braita sounds to be that it's biblical, which is ריש
לקיש's Reish Lakish position, and the other ברייתא braita says you bring
it and you don't say it, which sounds to be like רבי
יוחנן's position. At least that it's not biblical, maybe it's rabbinic, but
at least it's not biblical. So can each
position deal with both ברייתות? braitot? Let's take a look. בשלמא ריש
לקיש, Reish Lakish we can work it out for ריש לקיש, Reish
Lakish. both ברייתות braitot can work. גג אגג לא קשיא, Gag a-gag
lo kashya, it's not difficult that one says the rooftop you bring
and you make the declaration and the other says you don't make
the declaration. הא בגג דמערה הא בגג דבית. Ha be-gag de-me'ara ha
be-gag de-bayit.
Where is it a rooftop of? Is it a basically—even if it's
not ideal, it has to grow from the ground. And the גמרא
basically feels if you have dirt that's off of the ground, it's
not considered growing from the earth, right? It may be growing from
dirt, but not from the earth, not from the land of Israel.
So where is this rooftop? You could have the roof of a
cave, the roof of a cave is
earth—is earth, right? So that might not be the ideal place for
growing because if it's a cave it doesn't have all the nutrients
going deep down, right? It sort of stops pretty soon, but nevertheless
it's earth. So there, there you would actually bring and read because
it's growing from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. If you have a rooftop
garden and it's the roof of your building, it's not ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael ground, growing straight from the land and therefore even if
you bring you don't—it's not biblical, you don't make the declaration. Okay,
similarly חורבה אחורבה לא קשיא, churba a-churba lo kashya, sort of a
vacant field and a vacant field. One seems like it is an
obligation, the other not. That's not a problem. כאן בחורבה עבודה כאן
בחורבה שאינה עבודה. Kan be-churba avuda kan be-churba she-eina avuda. Have you
actually plowed the field or not? Because here we're assuming that the
ביכורי מעשיך, bikurei ma'asecha, it has to be the ביכורים of your
labor. So if stuff that just grew wild, that would not be
biblical. But if you actually plowed this vacant field and planted on
it even though, again, it's not
nutrient-rich, it's basically a dirt lot and so on, nevertheless you would
still be biblical. So again, what we're saying is ריש לקיש can
make it work. ריש לקיש allows for the fact that you bring
ביכורים from these non-ideal places—I mean he only
says from the—from the שבעה מינים, shiv'at minim, but not the ביכורים?
Right. Right. Yeah. So anyway ריש לקיש allows for the fact that
you can bring ביכורים from these non-ideal places and that's the ברייתא
braita that says מביא וקורא, mevi ve-kore, but what he doesn't allow
for is—is that A) it has to be מעשיך, ma'asecha, can't be
by itself; B) it has to grow from the actual land of
Israel. So that's the ברייתא that says מביא ואינו קורא. mevi ve-eino
kore. So let's just finish this up for ריש לקיש.
עציץ אעציץ לא קשיא, Atzitz a-atzitz lo kashya, how about the flowerpot?
One says you make the declaration, one says you don't. כאן בנקוב
כאן בשאינו נקוב. Kan be-nakuv kan be-she-eino nakuv. So does the flowerpot
have a hole in it? Right, the גמרא says if you've got
a flowerpot on the ground and it's got a hole in it,
then you see it as like just a little bump on the
ground. Okay, and it's like it's growing straight from the earth. Then,
again, not ideal, but you would still bring and you would still
be קורא, kore, it's growing from the ground. If it's without a
hole in it, it's not growing from the actual land of Israel,
it's in dirt but not the land of Israel, then you bring
but you're לא קורא, lo kore, you're not biblically obligated. And finally
ספינה אספינה לא קשיא, sfina a-sfina lo kashya, the case of the
boat is not difficult. This is going to be interesting—how can the
boat be considered to be growing from the land of Israel? So
it's going to say, כאן בספינה של עץ כאן בספינה של חרס.
Kan be-sfina shel etz kan be-sfina shel cheres. Okay now if it
is a—here's a big תוספות Tosafot that figures out what this answer
means, but they're basically two ways of understanding. One is the boat's
assumed if it's wood, wood is considered to separate... separate between what's
growing and the earth below and therefore it's not biblically it's not
growing from the land of Israel and therefore you bring rabbinically but
you don't make the declaration
that's just the leaky boat that's been grounded.
Oh wow. Thank you. How did you know that? But you guessed.
That's exactly what תוספות Tosafot said. No in order for it to
be considered growing from the land of Israel first of all it
has to be pottery it has to be pottery which is porous
as opposed to wood. Number two what this גמרא is not saying
but another גמרא says another משנה Mishna says whatever is it has
to be grounded. The bottom of the hull has to be it's
growing by the way is it called the hull the bottom part?
It's growing in dirt in the hull not on the deck. The
hull is in the actual dirt of the sea bottom. And the
third point you said leaky was brilliant. Exactly תוספות. Tosafot. There's actually
תוספות Tosafot has two opinions. רש"י says no if it's pottery and
in the ground it doesn't have to be leaky that doesn't need
a hole in it. But תוספות Tosafot is inclined to say that
no we normally talk about an עציץ נקוב Atitz Nakuv it should
be no different here. So תוספות Tosafot says it needs exactly all
the three things you said. It has to be pottery a boat
of pottery go figure which is porous it has to be in
the sea bottom or river bed and it has to have a
hole in it.
That's life in the riverbed.
Okay. So tomorrow we will find out how ר' יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
deals with these
two things.